Guide to the National Defense Education Act, Counseling and Guidance Institutes, Records
Stanford University. Libraries.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
National Defense Education Act, Counseling and Guidance Institutes, records
1965-1968
SC0155
National Defense Education Act. Counseling and Guidance Institutes.
3 Linear feet
Records include correspondence, applications, memoranda, papers presented, reports and general material relating to the institutes held in the summers of 1965 and 1966 and one workshop held in October 1967.
Department of Special Collections and University Archives Green Library 557 Escondido Mall Stanford, CA 94305-6064 Email: specialcollections@stanford.edu Phone: (650) 725-1022 URL: http://library.stanford.edu/spc
Administrative Information
Provenance
Administrative transfer, 1977.
Information about Access
This collection is open for research.
Biographical/Historical Sketch
The National Defense Education Act (Public Law 85-864) of 1958, amended in November 1964, provided for guidance and counseling institutes to be held at various institutions across the country, with the purpose of training counselors at all academic levels to work more effectively with disadvantaged and minority students who are facing vocational decisions. Stanford was chosen as a host institution. Dr. John D. Black, Director of the Stanford University Counseling and Testing Center, directed the two institutes and one workshop held on the Stanford campus in 1965, 1966, and October 1967.
Description of the Collection
Records include correspondence, applications, memoranda, papers presented, reports and general material relating to the institutes held in the summers of 1965 and 1966 and one workshop held in October 1967.
Access Terms
Black, John D.; National Defense Education Act. Counseling and Guidance Institutes.; United States. National Defense Education Act.; Counseling in higher education --United States.
Collection Contents
- NDEA Counseling and Guidance Institute, June 20-July 31, 1965
  - Act, NDE; Congressional material (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Applicants – requests for information – qualified (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Applicants – requests for information – unqualified, A – H (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Applicants – requests for information – unqualified, I – Z (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Application forms mailed (not completed) (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Application forms – incomplete – Davis, Luther E. (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Application forms – incomplete – Hepp, Joseph L. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Application forms – incomplete – Kirk, Erle R. (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Application forms – incomplete – McManus, Betty D. (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Application forms – incomplete – Robinson, James (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Application forms – incomplete – Varelas, James (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Application materials (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bulletins sent enrollees (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence – form letters (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence – miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Counselor programs and projections – Hilsinger (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Enrollees – Addresses (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Enrollees – Data re. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Faculty/Staff (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Finance (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Forms, miscellaneous (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Group reports (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Lecturers (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Local arrangements (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Manual (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Maps (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Miscellaneous dittoed work (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Papers presented (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Plan of operation (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Policies and procedures (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Proposals (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Publicity (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Report (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Schedules – enrollees' activities (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Stipend, request for (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Suggestions (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Summary report (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Topics of interest (answer forms) (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - U.S. Office of Education – corresp0ndence (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - U.S. Office of Education – memos (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Institutes, other – A - Md (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Institutes, other – Mich. - Z (Box 1, Folder 42)
- NDEA Counseling and Guidance Institute, June 20-July 29, 1966
  - Act - NDE (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Applicants – accepted (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Applications – circulating for rating (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Application forms (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Application requests – qualified (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Bibliographies (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Bulletins to enrollees (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Check-list, blank (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Contract (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence – form letters (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence – miscellaneous (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence – U.S. Office of Education, bulletins and memos (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence – U.S. Office of Education, general (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Course materials and papers (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Course materials – ditto masters (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Enrollees, data on (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Evaluation (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Faculty/Staff (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Finance (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Groups, etc. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Housing (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Institutes – other (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Lecturers (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Local arrangements (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - MacNaughton, William S. (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Manuals (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Maps (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Oath (forms) (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Preliminary report (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Proposal (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Publicity (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Rating forms (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Records (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Report (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Research projects (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Sample material for report (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Social security numbers (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Stipend requests and forms (Box 4, Folder 2)
- Other NDEA Material
  - Correspondence, general, 1966-67 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Proposed NDEA Institute 1967 – masters (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Proposed NDEA Institute 1967 – institutional research (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Proposed NDEA Institute 1967 – proposal (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Rating, including summary, [1967?] (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Proposed NDEA Institute 1968 – correspondence, requests for information (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Proposed NDEA Institute 1968 – proposal (Box 4, Folder 9)